Ben Dalton

COMMUNICATIONS + TECH

daltonwb@gmail.com benjamindalton.com 202-413-4447

Profile

Communicate policy research and recommendations to global audiences for the International Crisis Group, a leading non-governmental conflict prevention organization. Write, edit, and place commentary in top North American outlets; code data visualizations and custom maps using the latest tools and standards; and publish photography in outlets like the *Christian Science Monitor* and *Vice*. Provide time-sensitive IT support to staff around the world and directly manage the IT resources for Crisis Group's Washington and New York offices.

Dedicated to telling stories that matter in compelling, accessible ways using web technologies that are powerful, innovative, and eye-catching.

Work Experience

Communications & IT Officer

April 2011 - PRESENT

International Crisis Group

- Conceive and create data visualizations and interactive maps using photos, video, HTML/ CSS, JavaScript, and GIS to communicate Crisis Group's research and policy recommendations to core and expanding audiences.
- Write, edit, and place commentary pieces in leading national outlets.
- Develop and administer Crisis Group's web presence, including the primary site, a network of WordPress blogs, and social media accounts including Twitter, Tumblr, Facebook, Google+, and others.
- Manage publicity for Crisis Group analysts, pitching interviews and stories to top print and broadcast outlets. Ensure that Crisis Group's take on breaking news is well represented in new and traditional media.
- Produce video and other multimedia for the web and events like Crisis Group's New York
 Gala, the organization's signature award ceremony, which has honored figures like Hillary
 Clinton and George Soros.
- Served as field producer, videographer, and audio recordist while filming in countries like Libya, Turkey, Kenya, Georgia, and Kazakhstan.
- Manage IT resources for offices in Washington, DC, and New York City; provide support to staff in dozens of offices worldwide.
- Manage rotating team of two to four interns.

Media Intern

August 2010 - March 2011

International Crisis Group

- Researched and drafted written products for target media such as Foreign Policy magazine and the Miami Herald.
- Produced podcasts, videos, and other online content.
- Pitched articles and interviews to media outlets.
- Coordinated media appearances of Crisis Group analysts.

Publicity Assistant

June 2010 - August 2010

Harvard University Press

- Designed publicity campaigns for paperback releases covering philosophy, history, and current affairs.
- Directed workflow among publicists.
- Maintained Harvard's publicity databases.

Skills

HTML, CSS, & JavaScript

ADVANCED

- Design and code web apps, data visualizations, maps, and custom sites, often built for non-technical end users.
- Experience with Google Maps API v3, leaflet.js, d3.js, jQuery, and other JavaScript libraries, as well as JavaScript-based languages like Google Apps Script.
- Comfortable with popular content management systems, including WordPress, Sitecore, and Drupal.
- Tight integration of Adobe Creative Cloud applications like Photoshop and Illustrator into web development workflow.

Audiovisual Media

ADVANCED

- Shoot, edit, and produce audio and video products for Crisis Group, including the organization's podcast series, YouTube videos, and event material.
- Proficient with Adobe Premiere CC, Final Cut, recording video and sound in both studio and field environments, digital photography and editing.

Writing

- Draft, edit, and place opinion pieces in top outlets, including two bylines on CNN.com.
- Proficient with a range of writing styles, including news writing, op-eds, technical writing, and blogging. Edit for content and copy edit according to AP and Economist styles.

Languages

INTERMEDIATE

ADVANCED

- Four years of college **Russian**, including a semester of study abroad in Irkutsk, Russia.
- Extensive use of Russian while shooting photos and video in Georgia and Kazakhstan.
- Certified by the Goethe Institute, Göttingen, Germany, at the advanced intermediate level (ZMP) in German

Fellowships & Awards

Kazakhstan Fellow

August 2013

- International Reporting Project
- Reported from Kazakhstan as part of a small team of media professionals, covering security, cultural, and environmental issues.
- Published photos with the Christian Science Monitor, Vice, New Eurasia, Crisis Group, and other outlets.

Eagle Scout

2005

Boy Scouts of America

Education

Brown University

BA, International Relations — 3.95 GPA

- Graduated magna cum laude, member of Phi Beta Kappa Society
- Study abroad in Russia and India
- Contributing writer, College Hill Independent